Guide to the Louis Fischer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Louis Fischer papers
1929-1961
MS 214
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
Family and professional correspondence and typescript drafts of four books published between 1942 and 1962. His major correspondent is G.V. Chicherin, a Russian diplomat, who wrote to protest passages in Fischer's book, The Soviets in World Affairs, relating to Soviet affairs in the Revolutionary period.
Fischer, Louis, 1896-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis Fischer 1946-1961.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Louis Fischer Papers contain correspondence and typescript drafts of four books by Fischer. Fischer's correspondence consists of letters to, from and about Georgii Vasil'evich Chicherin concerning Fischer's book, The Soviets in World Affairs, published in 1930. (References to page numbers in the correspondence are to the proofs of the book.) Chicherin was sending corrections and comments on affairs in Russia from before the Revolution through the 1920s, and discussing as well matters of policy, personal affairs, and his deteriorating physical and emotional state. He began to accuse Fischer of misrepresenting his actions and political views during the 1918 landing of Allied troops at Murmansk, and grew increasingly upset, to the point where he claimed to be "near to suicide" due to Fischer (1930 Aug 28). Fischer described visits to Chicherin in two letters to his wife, Bertha (Mark) Fischer, and eventually sent a letter for publication (probably in The Nation\) to clarify Chicherin's actions at Murmansk.
These papers were given to Yale University by Louis Fischer in a series of gifts in 1946-1947 and 1961.
Biographical / Historical
Journalist; author and editor of numerous articles and books about the Soviet Union published from 1917-1969: Four of his books are: Gandhi and Stalin, Men and Politics, Russia, America, and the World, and The Story of Indonesia.
Europe; Soviet Union -- Politics and government; Soviet Union; Journalists; Chīcherīn, Georgiĭ Vasīl'evīch, 1872-1936; Fischer, Louis, 1896-1970
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Chicherin, Georgii Vasil'evich, to Louis Fischer, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Fischer, Louis
      - Letters to G. V. Chicherin, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Letters to "Markooska" [i.e., Bertha (Mark) Fischer], 1929 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letter to the editor [probably of ] The Nation, 1932 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Tatiana" to Louis Fischer, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings
    - Gandhi and Stalin, [1947?] (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
    - Men and Politics, [1941?] (Box 1, Folder 10 - 12)
    - Russia, America, and the World, [1961?] (Box 2, Folder 13 - 14)
    - The Story of Indonesia, [1959?] (Box 2, Folder 15 - 17)